Are you tired of your boss?
هل سئمتم من مديركم في العمل؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Are you tired of going to work
هل سئمتم من الذهاب للعمل
and making money for other people?
وكسب المال لأجل آخرين؟
And who are those people anyways?
ومن هم هؤلاء الناس بأي حال؟
Those people that make money from your work.
هؤلاء الذين يجنون المال من عملكم أنتم.
Well, they're capitalists.
حسنًا، هم رأسماليون.
They have capital,
يمتلكون رأس المال،
and they use your labor to make more capital.
ويستغلون عملكم لكسب المزيد منه.
So if you're tired of going to work
لذا إذا سئمتم من الذهاب للعمل
and making money for other people,
وكسب المال لأجل آخرين،
then you're probably like me --
فعلى الأرجح أنتم مثلي،
just tired of capitalism.
سئمتم من الرأسمالية.
Which is ironic, because I'm a capitalist.
وهذا مثير للسخرية، لأني رأسمالية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I own a small business --
أمتلك شركة صغيرة،
Rco Tires in Compton.
شركة (آر سي أو تايرز) في (كومبتون)،
A few years ago, when I read Van Jones,
قبل بضع سنوات، عندما قرأت (فان جونز)،
and he wrote, "Let's make green collar jobs in the hood,"
وكتب: "دعونا نوفر وظائف تحافظ على البيئة في الحي،"
I took him really seriously.
أخذت كلامه على محمل الجد.
So I cofounded, own and operate a tire recycling company,
لذا أسست شركة لإعادة تدوير الإطارات وامتلكتها وشغلتها،
and I'm really proud of what we've done.
وأنا فخورة للغاية بما حققناه.
So far, we've recycled a hundred million pounds of rubber.
حتى الآن، أعدنا تدوير مائة مليون رطل من المطاط.
That's 21 million gallons of oil diverted from landfills
هذا يعادل 21 مليون جالون من الزيت المُلقى في مدافن القمامة
into new products.
تم تحويله إلى منتجات جديدة.
(Cheers)
(هتافات)
We also employ about 15 guys --
نوظف أيضًا ما يقرب من 15 عامل،
mostly people of color,
أغلبهم من أصحاب البشرة السوداء،
most of whom are felons,
وأغلبهم متورطين في جنح،
and we pay above the minimum wage,
وندفع لهم رواتب تزيد عن الحد الأدنى،
and we are now proud members of the United Steelworkers Union.
ونعتز بعضويتنا في نقابة عمال صناعة الصلب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, Rco is not a cooperative now.
الآن، (آر سي أو) ليست شركة تعاونية.
It's a privately held company with community-minded ownership,
هي شركة ذات ملكية خاصة وتهتم بالمجتمع المحلي.
but I would like it to become one.
لكني أود أن تصبح شركة تعاونية.
I would like for them to fire the boss --
أود أن يطرد العمال رؤساءهم،
that's me.
أي يطردوني أنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm going to tell you why,
وسأخبركم السبب،
but first, let me tell you how we got started.
لكن أولًا دعوني أخبركم عن بدايتنا.
So a lot of people ask,
يسأل الجميع:
"How did Rco come to be?"
"كيف تأسست (آر سي أو)؟"
And I have to be really honest.
وسأكون صادقة للغاية.
I leveraged my white privilege.
استفدت من ميزة بشرتي البيضاء.
So, here's how white privilege worked for me and Rco.
وإليكم كيف أثرت ميزة البشرة البيضاء عليّ وعلى شركتي.
My white grandmother was born on her family's plantation
ولدت جدتي البيضاء في مزرعة عائلتها
in Arkansas in 1918.
في (أركنساس)، عام 1918.
She traveled with her white father west,
سافرت مع والدها الأبيض غربًا،
following the oil boom.
في أعقاب فترة ازدهار النفط.
And he held various union oil jobs --
وعمل بوظائف عديدة في اتحاد النفط،
jobs which would have never been given to my black great-grandfather,
وظائف لم يكن ليحصل عليها جدي الأكبر الأسود
had he lived here at the time.
إذا كان يعيش هناك في تلك الفترة.
Granny became a hairdresser
أصبحت جدتي مصففة شعر
and then got a loan with her husband
وحصلت على قرض مع زوجها
who built their home in West Los Angeles --
وبنوا بيتهم في غرب (لوس أنجلوس)،
a loan which would never have been given to a black family at the time.
هذا القرض لم يكن ليُعطى لعائلة سوداء في ذلك الوقت.
And after my grandfather passed away,
وبعد وفاة جدي،
my granny was able to keep that house
تمكنت جدتي من الحفاظ على ذلك المنزل
because she had his pension and his health care
لأنها حصلت على معاشه وبطاقة رعايته الصحية
from a state job which he held,
من وظيفة حكومية كان يعمل بها،
which again, would have never been given to a black man
مرة أخرى، وظيفة لم تكن لتمنح لرجل أسود
before the anti-discrimination act of the 1960s.
قبل إصدار قانون "مناهضة التمييز" في الستينات.
So, you fast-forward 30 years,
لذا، بعد 30 سنة من ذلك الوقت،
and I graduate,
تخرجتُ،
and I want to start my own business
وأردت إنشاء عملي الخاص
with a pile of debt and a credit card,
مع حزمة من الديون وبطاقة ائتمانية،
and no experience in the tire industry.
وليس عندي خبرة في صناعة الإطارات.
But I had what most people didn't have.
لكن كنت أمتلك ما لم يمتلكه غيري.
I had a clean, safe, free place to live.
كنت أمتلك مكانًا نظيفًا وآمنًا ومجانيًا.
I moved in with my grandmother,
انتقلت للعيش مع جدتي،
and I was able to rent our first warehouse,
وتمكنت من تأجير أول مخزن لنا،
buy our first truck,
وبيع أول شاحنة لنا،
pay our first employees,
ودفع رواتب لموظفينا الأوائل،
because I didn't have to worry about paying myself,
لأني لم أكن أقلق بشأن الدفع بنفسي،
because I didn't need to feed myself,
لأني لم أكن بحاجة إلى إطعام نفسي،
because I am the direct beneficiary of generations of white privilege.
لأني المستفيدة المباشرة من الأجيال صاحبة ميزة البشرة البيضاء.
Now, telling the story of white privilege is important
يعد سرد قصة ميزة البشرة البيضاء مهمًا
because very often people say,
لأن العديد من الأشخاص يقولون:
"Oh, we want more companies like yours.
"آه، نريد مزيد من الشركات مثل شركتك.
We want more Rco's,
نريد المزيد من (آر سي أو)
we want more black-owned businesses,
نريد المزيد من الشركات المملوكة للسود،
female-led, triple bottom line,
وشركات تديرها سيدات طبقًا للمعايير الثلاثية الأساسية،
Ban the Box,
ولا تسأل عن الماضي الجنائي،
green manufacturing companies," right?
وشركات تصنيع محافظة على البيئة،" صحيح؟
But the question we have to ask is, where is the wealth?
لكن السؤال الذي علينا طرحه هو: أين الثروة؟
Where is the money?
أين المال؟
And in telling a story of the white side of my family,
وفي سرد قصة الجانب الأبيض من عائلتي،
I needed a dozen ways
كنت بحاجة لمئات الطرق
where blacks were excluded from the economy,
حيث كان يُطرد السود من الاقتصاد،
whereas the white side of my family was able to gain access and traction,
كما كان الجانب الأبيض من عائلتي قادرًا على الوصول والجذب،
and build wealth ...
وبناء الثروات،
Primarily because racism and capitalism are best homies, but --
في المقام الأول لأن العنصرية والرأسمالية يمثلان أفضل ثنائي،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but what that means is that when we ask ourselves,
لكن معنى هذا أنه عندما نسأل أنفسنا،
"Why are our communities broke?" --
"لماذا تفلس مجتمعاتنا؟"
Like, we're not just broke because we're broke;
لأننا لا نفلس ببساطة هكذا؛
we're broke for a reason.
نتعرض للإفلاس لسبب ما.
Historical context really does matter.
يمثل السياق التاريخي أهمية.
But our history tells another story as well.
لكن تاريخنا يروي قصة أخرى أيضًا.
There's this incredible book called "Collective Courage,"
يوجد كتاب مذهل بعنوان "الشجاعة الجماعية،"
which is the story of how thousands of African Americans
والذي يعبر عن آلاف الأمريكيين الأفارقة
have been able to build businesses and schools,
الذين أسسوا الشركات والمدارس،
hospitals, farming cooperatives,
والمستشفيات وشركات الزراعة،
banks, financial institutions --
والبنوك والمؤسسات المالية،
entire communities and sovereign economies,
ومجتمعات بأكملها واقتصادات سيادية،
without a lot of capital.
بدون توافر الكثير من رأس المال.
And they did it by working together
وفعلوا ذلك بالعمل سويًا
and leveraging their community assets
وتعزيز أصولهم المجتمعية
and trusting each other
والوثوق ببعضهم البعض
and putting solidarity first --
وجعْل الأولوية للتضامن،
not just profits by any means necessary.
لا لجمع الأرباح بأي وسيلة ضرورية.
And they didn't have to wait around for celebrities and athletes
ولم يلجأوا إلى انتظار المشاهير والرياضيين
to bring their money back to the hood.
لجلب أموالهم إلى الحي.
However, if you are a celebrity or an athlete,
برغم ذلك، إذا كنت من المشاهير أو الرياضيين
and you're listening to this,
وتستمع لكلامي هذا،
please feel free to bring your money.
رجاءً لا تتردد في جلب أموالك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But they did it through cooperative economics,
لكنهم فعلوا ذلك خلال الاقتصاد التعاوني،
because they knew
لأنهم أدركوا
that capitalism was never going to finance black liberation.
أن الرأسمالية لم تكن أبدًا لتموّل تحرير السود.
So, there are so many great examples in this book,
ومن ثم يوجد أمثلة عديدة في هذا الكتاب،
and I suggest that everybody just read it
وأوصي بأن يقرأه الجميع
because it answers the question I asked earlier,
لأنه يجيب عن السؤال الذي طرحته سابقًا،
which was where are we going to get the wealth
وهو من أين نحصل على الثروة
to build the types of business that we want.
لتأسيس مختلف الأعمال التي نريدها؟
And the answer is going to have to be cooperative economics.
والإجابة ستكون في الاقتصاد التعاوني.
There's a lot of different versions of cooperativism.
يوجد العديد من التصورات حول التعاونيات.
What I'm talking about today is worker ownership.
الذي أتحدث عنه اليوم هو ملكية العمال.
You may not have heard of worker ownership,
ربما لم يسمع أحد عن ملكية العمال بعد.
but it's been an incredible tool
لكنها كانت وسيلة مذهلة
for black economic liberation for a century,
لتحرير اقتصاد السود لمدة قرن،
and it's also working all over the world right now.
وأيضًا آخذة في الانتشار حول العالم.
You may have heard of Black Wall Street
ربما سمعتم عن (بلاك وول ستريت)
or maybe the Zapatistas,
أو ربما (زاباتستاس)،
but I'll give you an example that's a little bit closer to home.
لكني سأعطيكم مثالًا قريبًا منكم.
Right now, today, in South Bronx,
الآن، اليوم، في جنوب (برونكس)،
is the country's largest worker-owned company.
يوجد أكبر شركة مملوكة للعمال في الدولة.
It's called Cooperative Home Care Associates,
اسمها (شركة الرعاية المنزلية التعاونية)،
and it was founded by black and Latinx home care workers
أسستها عاملات سمراوات لاتينيات في مجال الرعاية المنزلية
who are now able to pay themselves living wages,
ويقدرن على دفع أجور المعيشة بأنفسهن،
they have full-time hours,
ويعملن ساعات عمل كاملة،
they have benefits and a pension,
ويحصلن على أرباح ومعاشات،
through their membership as a unit of SEIU.
خلال عضويتهن في نقابة موظفي الخدمات.
And these women owners now receive a dividend back on their ownership
وتحصل هؤلاء السيدات على مكاسب مقابل ملكيتهن
every year that the company has been profitable,
كل عام عند حصول الشركة على أرباح،
which has been most years.
وذلك يكون في معظم الأعوام.
So they're able to really enjoy the fruits of their labor
لذلك يتمتع العمال بثمار عملهم
because they fired the boss.
لأنهم طردوا رؤساء العمل.
They don't have any big investors.
ليس لديهم أي مستثمر رئيسي.
They don't have fat-cat CEOs
وليس لديهم مدير تنفيذي مهتم بالربح فقط
or absentee owners taking the profit out of the company.
أو المالِك المتغيب الذي يقبض أرباح الشركة فقط.
They each pay in about 1,000 dollars over time
يدفع العمال 1,000 دولار من العمل لساعات إضافية
in order to gain ownership,
للحصول على الملكية،
and now they own their job.
والآن هم يمتلكون وظائفهم.
Now, there's hundreds of more examples of companies like this
يوجد أمثلة عديدة على شركات من هذا النوع
springing up all across the country.
بدأت بالظهور في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
And I'm so inspired by what they're doing,
وما يفعلونه يلهمني كثيرًا،
because it really represents an alternative
لأنهم يقدمون بديلًا
to the type of economy we have now,
للشركات المتواجدة الآن،
which exploits all of us.
التي تستغلنا جميعًا.
It also represents an alternative
وتشكل أيضًا بديلًا
to waiting around for big investors to bring chain stores,
للانتظار من أجل المستثمرين الكبار لبناء سلسلة متاجر،
or big-box stores to our communities,
أو بناء متاجر كبرى في مجتمعاتنا،
because honestly, those types of developments,
لأن بصراحة، هذه التطورات،
they steal resources from our communities.
تسرق الموارد من مجتمعاتنا.
They put our mom-and-pop shops out of business,
فهي تضع المحلات الصغيرة خارج المنافسة،
they make our entrepreneurs into wage workers,
وتجعل رواد الأعمال مثل العمال المأجورين،
and they take money out of our pocket
ويأخذون الأموال من جيوبنا
and send it to their shareholders.
ويرسلونها إلى المساهمين.
So, I was so inspired by all these stories of resistance and resilience
ألهمتني جميع هذه القصص عن الكفاح والصمود
that I got together with a few people here in Los Angeles,
الذين رأيتهما لدى بعض الناس هنا في (لوس أنجلوس)،
and we created LUCI.
وأنشأنا (لوسي).
LUCI stands for the Los Angeles Union Cooperative Initiative,
وهي اختصار لـ(مبادرة نقابة لوس أنجلوس التعاونية)،
and our objective is to create more worker-owned businesses
وهدفنا هو إنشاء شركات مملوكة للعمال
here in Los Angeles.
هنا في (لوس أنجلوس).
So far, in the last year, we've created two:
حتى الآن في العام الماضي أنشأنا شركتين:
Pacific Electric, an electrical company,
(باسيفيك إليكتريك)، شركة مختصة بالكهرباء،
and Vermont Gage Carwash,
وشركة (فيرمونت) لغسيل السيارات،
which is right here in South-Central,
ومقرها هنا في (ساوث سنترال)،
some of you guys might be familiar with it.
ربما يعرفها بعضكم،
This long-time carwash is now owned and operated by its 20 workers,
أصبحت الآن بعد هذه المدة الطويلة مملوكة لعمالها الـ20 ويشغلونها،
all of whom are union members as well.
وجميعهم أعضاء في النقابة أيضًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So you might be wondering why the focus on union-worker ownership,
ربما تتساءلون عن سبب التركيز على ملكية عمال النقابات.
but there's a lot of good reasons
هناك الكثير من الأسباب المقنعة
why the labor movement is a natural ally to the worker-ownership movement.
لتكون الحركات العمالية حليف طبيعي للحركات الداعية لملكية العمال.
To build these companies that we want in our community,
لبناء هذه الشركات التي نريدها في مجتمعنا،
we need a few things.
نحتاج بعض الأشياء.
We're going to need money, people and training.
نحتاج المال والقوى العاملة والتدريب.
Unions have all of those things.
تمتلك النقابات جميع هذه العناصر.
America's working class has been paying union dues for decades,
تدفع الطبقة العاملة في أمريكا الرسوم للنقابات على مدى عقود،
and with it, our unions have been building
وتبني لنا النقابات بهذه الأموال
dignified, decent, and democratic workplaces for us.
أماكن عمل كريمة ولائقة وديمقراطية.
However, union jobs are on the steep decline,
مع ذلك انخفضت الوظائف النقابية بشدة،
and it's time for us to start calling on our unions
وحان الوقت لنبدأ بدعوة النقابات
to really bring all of their financial and political capital
لأن تستثمر رأس مالها المالي والسياسي
to bear in the creation of new, union, living-wage jobs
في إيجاد وظائف نقابية جديدة وتكفي للمعيشة
in our communities.
في مجتمعاتنا.
Also, union halls are full of union members
تمتلئ القاعات النقابية بالأعضاء
who understand the importance of solidarity
الذين يدركون أهمية التضامن
and the power of collective action.
وقوة العمل الجماعي.
These are the types of folks that want more union businesses to exist,
هذه هي مجموعة الناس التي تريد إيجاد المزيد من الأعمال التجارية النقابية،
so let's build them with them.
لذا دعونا نبنيها معهم.
Learning from our unions,
بالتعلم من النقابات،
learning from our past,
واستخلاص الدروس من الماضي،
learning from our peers,
والاستفادة من زملائنا،
are all going to be very important to our success,
جميعها سيضيف إلى أهمية نجاحنا،
which is why I'd like to leave you with one last example
والسبب في أني أود أن أعطيكم هذا المثال الأخير
and a vision for the future ...
ورؤية للمستقبل ...
and that vision is Mondragon, Spain.
تكمن هذه الرؤية في (موندراغون- إسبانيا).
Mondragon, Spain is a community built entirely around worker cooperatives.
تعد هذه البلدة مجتمعًا يتمحور حول التعاونيات العمالية.
There's 260-plus businesses here,
هناك ما يزيد عن 260 شركة هنا،
manufacturing everything from bicycles to washing machines to transformers.
تعمل على تصنيع كل شيء من الدراجات والغسالات والمحولات.
And this group of businesses now employs 80,000 people
وتوظف هذه الشركات 80,000 عامل
and earns more than 12 billion euros in revenue every year.
وتربح أكثر من 12 مليون يورو من الإيرادات كل عام.
And all of the companies there are owned by the people that work in them.
وجميع الشركات هناك يملكها العاملين فيها.
They've also built universities and hospitals and financial institutions.
وبنوا أيضًا جامعات ومستشفيات ومؤسسات مالية
I mean, imagine if we could build something like this in South-Central.
تخيلوا لو أن في إمكاننا بناء شركات كهذه في (ساوث سنترال).
The late mayor of Jackson had a similar idea.
عمدة (جاكسون) الراحل كانت لديه فكرة مشابهة.
He wanted to turn his entire city into a Mondragon-like cooperative economy,
أراد أن يحول اقتصاد المدينة بأكملها إلى الاقتصاد التعاوني مثل (موندراجون)،
calling his ambitious plan "Jackson Rising."
وأطلق على خطته الطموحة اسم "نهضة جاكسون."
And when I look at Mondragon,
وعندما أنظر إلى (موندراجون)،
I see really what working-class people can do for ourselves
أرى بالفعل ما يمكن أن تفعله الطبقة العاملة
when we work together
عند التعاون سويًا
and make decisions for ourselves and each other
واتخاذ القرارات لنا ولأنفسهم
and our communities.
ولمجتمعاتنا.
And what's really incredible about Mondragon
والشيء المذهل عن (موندراجون)
is that while we are dreaming about them,
هو أنه بينما نحلم بمستقبلهم،
they are dreaming about us.
هم أيضًا يحلمون بمستقبلنا.
This community in Spain has decided to launch an international initiative
قرر المجتمع في إسبانيا بدء مبادرة عالمية
to create more communities like it all over the world,
لإنشاء المزيد من المجتمعات مثل (موندراجون) حول العالم،
by linking up with unions,
عن طريق التواصل مع النقابات،
by supporting organizations like LUCI,
ودعم المؤسسات مثل (لوسي)،
and by educating folks about the worker-ownership model.
وتثقيف الناس بشأن نموذج ملكية العمال.
Now, here's what you can do to be a part of it.
الآن، إليكم ما تستطيعون فعله لتنضموا إليه.
If you're a union member, go to your union meetings,
إذا كنتم أعضاء في نقابة، اذهبوا إلى الاجتماعات،
and make sure that your union has a worker-ownership initiative,
وتأكدوا من أن نقابتكم لديها مبادرة لملكية العمال،
and become a part of it.
واشتركوا بها.
If you're an entrepreneur,
إذا كنتم رواد أعمال،
if you have a small business,
إذا كان لديكم شركات صغيرة،
or you're interested in starting one,
أو كنتم مهتمين بإنشاء شركة،
then link up with LUCI or another organization like us
حينها تواصل مع (لوسي) أو مؤسسة أخرى مثلنا
to help you get started on the cooperative model.
لكي تساعدكم في البدء بنموذج التعاونيات.
If you're a politician,
إذا كنتم سياسيين،
or you work for one,
أو تعملون لديهم،
or you just like talking to them,
أو تحب فقط التحدث إليهم،
please get the city, state, federal and county legislation passed
رجاءً صدّق على القوانين الفدرالية الخاصة بالمدينة أو الولاية أو المقاطعة
that we need in order to fund and support worker-owned businesses.
التي نحتاجها لكي نموّل وندعم الشركات المملوكة للعمال.
And for everybody else,
وبالنسبة لأي شخص آخر،
learn about our history, learn about our models,
تعلموا من تاريخنا ومن نماذجنا،
and seek us out so can support us,
وابحثوا عنا بحيث تدعمونا،
you can buy from us, invest in us, lend to us and join us,
يمكنكم الشراء منا والاستثمار في مؤسساتنا وإقراضنا والانضمام إلينا،
because it's really going to take all of us
لأن ذلك سيقودنا جميعًا بالفعل
in order to build the more just and sustainable and resilient economy
لبناء اقتصاد أكثر عدلًا واستمرارية ومرونة
that we want for ourselves and our children.
الاقتصاد الذي نريده لأنفسنا وأبنائنا.
And with that,
وإضافة لذلك،
I would like to leave you with a quote from Arundhati Roy,
أود أن أقتبس كلامًا من (أروندهاتي روي)،
and she writes ...
كتبت قائلة:
"Our strategy should not be only to confront Empire,
"لا يجب أن تعتمد الاستراتيجية الخاصة بنا على التصدي للإمبراطورية،
but to lay siege to it.
لكن بفرض حصار عليها،
To deprive it of oxygen.
وحرمانها من مصدر حياتها،
To mock it.
والسخرية منها،
To shame it.
وإشعارها بالخزي،
With our art,
باستخدام الفن،
our literature,
والأدب،
our music,
والموسيقى،
our brilliance,
والعبقرية،
our joy,
والسعادة،
our sheer relentlessness --
والقسوة المفرطة،
and our ability to tell our own stories.
وقدرتنا على رواية قصصنا الخاصة،
Not the stories that we're being brainwashed to believe.
لا القصص التي جرى غسل أدمغتنا بها لنصدقها.
The corporate revolution will collapse
سوف تنهار ثورة الشركات
if we refuse to buy what they're selling --
إذا رفضنا شراء ما يعرضونه للبيع،
their ideas,
ورفض أفكارهم،
their version of history,
ورؤيتهم عن التاريخ،
their wars,
وحروبهم،
their weapons,
وأسلحتهم،
their sense of inevitability.
وإحساسهم بالحتمية.
Because know this:
لأننا نعلم هذا:
They be few and we be many.
هم يصبحون قلة ونحن نصبح كثرة.
They need us more than we need them.
هم بحاجة إلينا أكثر مما نحن بحاجة إليهم.
Another world is not only possible,
وجود عالم آخر ليس ممكنًا فحسب،
she's on her way.
بل يمضي في طريقه إلينا.
And on a quiet day,
وفي يوم هادئ،
I can hear her breathing."
أستطيع سماع أنفاسه."
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)